Guide to the Sergius Ossipovich Yakobson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sergius Ossipovich Yakobson Papers
1910-1979
1940-1969
MS 1419
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(6 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and topical files which document the professional career of Sergius Ossipovich Yakobson. The papers highlight his work in the Slavic Divison of the Library of Congress. Yakobson's writings on the history of Russia and the evolution of the Soviet state comprise over half the papers.
Yakobson, Sergius, 1901-1979
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1920-1973. II. SUBJECT FILES, 1910-1979. III. WRITINGS, 1943-1968.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Slavic and East European Collection, Sterling Memorial Library, 1985.
Biographical / Historical
Sergius Ossipovich Yakobson was born in Moscow on May 9, 1901. He received a Ph.D. from the University of Berlin and became a librarian and lecturer in Russian history at the University of London in 1926. In 1941 Yakobson began working at the Library of Congress. He became chief of the Slavic and Central European division in 1951 and served as senior specialist in Russian affairs until 1971. Yakobson died in Washington, D.C., on November 13, 1979.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Sergius Ossipovich Yakobson Papers consist of correspondence, articles, speeches, and topical files, which document the professional career of Sergius Ossipovich Yakobson. The papers highlight his work as chief of the Slavic and Central European Division of the Library of Congress and specialist in Russian affairs. Yakobson's writings on the history of Russia and the evolution of the Soviet state comprise over half the papers.
The papers, which were transferred to the Manuscripts and Archives Department in 1985 from the Sterling Memorial Library Slavic and East European Collection, are arranged in three series: I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1920-1973; II. SUBJECT FILES, 1910-1979; and III. WRITINGS, 1943-1968.
The bulk of the material dates from 1940 to 1969 and is in English. There are some writings and other documents also in Russian and German.
Series I contains Yakobson's correspondence with friends, and other Russian scholars. Correspondence with George Vernadsky and Dimitri Fedotoff White dates from Yakobson's first years in the United States. Exchanges with Harold Lasswell concern Yakobson's article, "May Day Slogans in Soviet Russia," in Language of Politics.
Series II, SUBJECT FILES, contains numerous descriptive lists and bibliographies relating to Russian collections. Materials filed under "Library of Congress" relate to the Slavic Collection which Yakobson helped develop at the Library of Congress. The series also includes personal memorabilia of Yakobson and writings, photographs, and documents of other family members.
Series III, WRITINGS, is composed of drafts, notes, background material, and printed copies for Yakobson's articles, speeches, and lectures. The writings reflect Yakobson's interests in Russian history, politics, and government, particularly Russian nationalism, the evolution of the Soviet state, and the Jewish population. Files for Yakobson's studies of May Day slogans (folders 34-35), his article "Russia and Africa" (folders 54-58), and his paper "Unpublished Letters of I. Turgenev" (folders 77-79) are particularly voluminous. Lectures (folders 44-47) and speeches (folders 69-74) are arranged in chronological order.
Jews -- Soviet Union; Nationalism -- Soviet Union; Propaganda, Communist -- Soviet Union; Soviet Union -- History; Soviet Union -- Politics and government; Historians; Librarians; Fedotoff White, D. (Dimitri), 1889-1950; Lasswell, Harold D. (Harold Dwight), 1902-1978; Vernadsky, George, 1887-1973; Yakobson, Sergius, 1901-1979; Library of Congress. Slavic and Central European Division
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1920-1973; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence in this series is arranged in alphabetical order by correspondents' names.
  - B - K, 1940-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - L - Z, 1920-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fedotoff White, D., 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Lasswell, Harold D., 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rand Corporation, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vernadsky, George, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Yale University, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified, 1940-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SUBJECT FILES, 1910-1979; Series II; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - French bibliographer's conference, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Katkov, M. (1841): transcribed letters, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Library of Congress, 1941-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Personal memorabilia
    - Jakobson, Ljubow, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    - Jakobson, Roman, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Photographs, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Yakobson, Sergius, 1910-1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Russia, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Slavic collections: descriptive lists, 1969-1979 (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
- WRITINGS, 1943-1968; Series III; 1.5' (4 boxes)
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by Yakobson's title or, when untitled, by subject.
  - "American-Russian Relations, 1937-1947", undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Aspects of Russian Nationalism", undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Basic Assumptions of Communist Propaganda", 1953 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Birobidjan", 1943 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Catherine the Great", undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Comparative Growth of Education in the USSR and China, The", undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Expansion, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "Far Eastern Policy", undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "First May Slogans, The", 1943 (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
  - "Five Letters of Jan Masaryk", undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - German translations, undated (Box 3, Folder 37-41)
  - "Growth of the Russian Population", 1943 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Jews in the USSR, The", 1950 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 4, Folder 44-47)
  - "'Mad Russian' Collector of 50 Picassos...", undated (Box 4, Folder 47a)
  - "Making of the Russian Frontiers, The", undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 49-50)
  - "Peter the Great", undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - "Problems and Prospects of Negotiating with the Russians", 1958 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - "Richard Cobden's Sojourn in Russia", undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - "Russia and Africa", undated (Box 4, Folder 54-58)
  - "Russia and Egypt", undated (Box 5, Folder 59-60)
  - "Russia's Early Conquest of Siberia", undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - "Siniavskii-Daniel Trial", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Soviet Censorship: book review, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - "Soviet Colonization Policy", undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Soviet nationalism, undated (Box 5, Folder 65-66)
  - "Soviet Technical Assistance Programs in Non-Communist Asia", undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - "Soviet Union and Point-Four", undated (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Speeches, 1950-1968, undated (Box 5, Folder 69-74)
  - "Tensions Within the Soviet Union", undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - "U.S.S.R. and Ethiopia, The", undated (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - "Unpublished Letters of I. Turgenev", undated (Box 6, Folder 77-79)
  - Fragments, undated (Box 6, Folder 80-81)